it may go all the way down to the
subatomic level that there's this
built-in mechanism that we express and
we we talk about it as desire but it
actually looks a lot more fundamental to
me than a word like desire this is real
interesting now I don't know how much as
a matter of content if your show kind of
goes into the deeply as a terror but
week a week that's the rabbit hole I'd
dive in real quick sure here it is a lot
so so one of the ways that I that I've
thought about it and this is and
basically just applying a framework that
I've used in the past that seems like it
might roughly fit not to over code the
domain were at but maybe get some some
directions I'm gonna get some
orientation on it is this is a
distinction that I've made between what
I've got what I call the rival wrist in
the ante rivalries which Maps roughly to
atoms and bits as it turns out which by
the way we should be very clear the
third term here which we might consider
energy to be a process or a dynamic
between the two so atoms bits and energy
feels like that's a pretty solid
constellation and we you know the
characteristic of the rival lists is
that is that it is rivalry a desire
competitive desire exactly at the end of
the day there are certain aspects of the
physical universe of which physics is
largely the thing the branch of science
that is that universe that are are at
the bottom strictly not shareable both
in the sense that they are atomic mean
if you have it I don't have it in some
sense and an entropic means that that to
the degree to which you interact with it
in any way you turn the free energy into
entropy you've depleted it permanently
in a one-way direction so there are
certain aspects of the universe the
things that are studied by physics that
have those characteristics and around
those aspects you would imagine that
they would evolve for example a as a
fundamental characteristic of any system
that
sorry I have to back up there's another
component here which has to do with the
irreducible necessity of the ability to
accumulate an upgrade Ian of that
particular scarce fundamental scarce
aspect of reality in order to perpetuate
dissipative systems right so we have
another thing here which I think you
just channeled there for a second I see
that yeah trying to think real deep oh
yeah no that's good the way this is
actually a secret but I'm I'm pretty
much a synesthete and I don't actually
think in words and so when I'm doing
that what I'm actually doing is trying
to hold a particular I kind of refer to
as a geometry but it's almost a little
bit more like you ever seen those
puzzles that are a 3d puzzle but you're
looking at it on a computer screen so
it's 2d right yeah you have to rotate it
and orient it until the 3d system it
pops and you see the 3d model yeah a bit
like that like I'm actually moving
things and some I don't know some
interior spaces but once it locks then I
have to hold it because it's not easy to
hold but once I hold it then I actually
starts figuring how to pull the words
out that
map to the thing but the things the
thing and that may very well be what's
referred to as channeling but yeah that
was that little bit right there was a
nice chunk of stuff I'm reasonably
confident and okay so you've got that
you've got dissipative systems and
you've got the the reality that there's
essentially a binary in dissipative
systems which is to say that either they
are what the lawyers would call heya
cities you might meet a simpler term
would be ephemeral like a yeah
a Scirocco or a little breeze you know
it comes around and it goes away
that's it evaporate and then that there
are others that have a capacity to pull
resources from their external
environment which now by definition are
going to be rivalries resources to
perpetuate their being what they are a
pattern that has the capacity to repeat
itself over time I'm pulling a lot of
right now a lot of Dolores and to a
lesser extent a lot into that
so you know and this by the way I had
this conversation with Brett Weinstein
about 12 years ago we're kind of
discussing ethics we got down to the
very bottom which is okay we can we can
make a proposition that we have a habit
of thought which is based on simple
survivor's bias we happen to be the
leading edge of a 13.7 billion year
survivor's bias those set that tiny
subset of all possible phenomena that
didn't just evaporate back into the
quantum phone and then you know so then
started getting atoms and the atoms
became molecules and didn't evaporate
back into the atomic you know maelstrom
and the molecules became organic
molecules didn't just evaporate back
where it's that structural development
where's this we have the survivors bias
of that and now kind of channel little
bit of Jordan Peterson here if you plug
him into that structure you're like yeah
and the narratives and Mister poetics
and ethos and values that we happen to
have sitting you know that we sit on top
of are an expression of that entire arc
of which now we can plug mimetic desire
is a real deep piece of that which
probably goes all the way down to the
struggle between quarks to be the ones
that actually turn into atoms right
right there at that pivot point between
to be and not to be or to continue to be
to become in becoming or to become
nothingness again is probably the the
pivot point and if you anchor there pull
all the way back out and can hold
continuity from the quantum foam all the
way up to you know complex cultures I
think then you've got a very fair frame
to actually start really talking about
the sorority and inside but to remember
that you're holding that piece of
reality which is the piece of reality
that's talking about the rival risk
talking about these characteristics of
the things that physics studies but then
we have to talk about the the other side
which has to do with creativity
emergence this is where Eric and I have
still never get finished I figured I had
to figure out our knife fight
and Brett I think sits in them in the
middle of it because he at the end of
the day as an evolutionary theorist
cannot dispense with the notion of
of evolution you can't dispense it the
notion that there is in fact change that
the that the the sort of Newtonian up to
turn in D I call the simple Einstein Ian
model of a all at once static space-time
continuum
in the notion that there is in fact no
novelty that all has in some sense
happen instantaneously and that to
degree to which we perceive change it's
an illusion
from an evolutionary theory perspective
that isn't a good a good model and
evolution theory it has to have at least
some notion that you can actually you
actually can go from 0 to 1 you can go
from what is to an entirely novel and
some in time some kind of actual novelty
like innovation innovation exists as a
part of ontology well ok that's the
other piece i Novation cannot be
strictly rivalries because at the very
beginning you're literally going from
zero to one you are in fact creating
mortis that piece is the piece that is
not fully captured in purely mimetic
desire because you you're actually
creating something new there is no copy
there so that would be the other the
other piece that I would lay her in to
get a fully rich theory things you've
got things like scarcity and then this
idea of maybe post scarcity here this
ideally I'm thinking of the the biblical
story of Jesus when he's handing out the
fishes and loaves and he takes these
fishes and loaves but they just keep
coming he doesn't he doesn't cut the
fish up into piece and I able to get a
little a little meat here no he's just
like no and it's this this declaration
of war against scarcity and it doesn't
require it doesn't require coercion to
do he doesn't he doesn't say all right
I'm forcing you to give me your food he
just voluntary exchange and from that
voluntary exchange there's this
renunciation of the confining power of
scarcity right well I mean that's
creativity without conflict right that's
that's creativity as generativity and as
you notice there's a whole bunch of
characteristics like if you think about
that particular parable there's a
mentality there's a premise there's a
commitment it's a piece for example yeah
you can't in fact have generativity
outside of peace peace is the space
which gives rise to the possibility of
true collaboration once you've achieved
peace you then have achieved the
capacity to shift from a scarcity
dynamic to an abundance dynamic plent
plenitude as a secondary air artifact
and I'm making that distinction so
I think of I think of there being a
scarcity mentality in it attached to the
scarcity mentality and we can actually
use we have shifting to the mythopoetic
I would tag the character of Mammon so
Mammon is what happens when you operate
with the scarcity mentality but x
grotesquerie so you know the Jabba the
Hutt character Jabba the Hutt is has too
much but still is tied to a scarcity
mentality and it's trying to plug the
hole of scarcity through getting more
that's the wrong answer then you got
another thing over here which we can
talk about Jesus and the parable which
is to say no we're actually going to
move into the abundance mentality we're
going to move into a space that is
anchored in a fundamental sense of
orienting towards this other domain the
domain of creativity domain of
generativity the germane domain of
Novation which first and foremost has to
be held in a space of peace but once
we're in that space we recognize a
renowned a place its place of plenitude
we're just necessarily even vaguely look
like Jabba the Hutt next looks nothing
at all like that there's like a whole
bunch of people who have actually have
to be conscious of the fact that it's
and to maintain the integrity of peace
is the first thing you have to do that's
the beginning you can't maintain the
integrity of peace and then the whole
plenitude evaporates and so therefore
each of us as an individual has to start
taking responsibility for only taking
that piece of the piece that is ours and
to carry the cross the desires to carry
it fully and completely to maintain the
integrity of that you know that thing is
the most sacred the most sacrosanct
yeah sorry okay what if I'd have been in
a tie right there
no but there's this idea that you don't
have to divide up the pieces that you
have that you can take what you have and
through voluntary sharing you can you
can't alleviate the the pressures of a
scarce world that you've got a whole
crowd here who's hungry who's gonna get
fed first
that's the question you'd immediately
think is it going to be the apostles or
is it going to be those who are richest
in the crowd who have fast passes to
Disney World
who's it going to be and this issue is
not resolved by saying okay let's let's
ration out what we have we've got a
basket of fish and loaves somehow in
that moment of voluntary sharing
scarcity is just overcome it's just its
disgust Lee has just thrown out the
window as if it doesn't actually bind up
the universe after all it's a lot of
powerful stuff in there too does if you
think about it there's a moment there's
a choice and a big part of that choice
has to do with fear you know if you're
able to choose in the face of fear is
that at that moment there's a hey who's
gonna get the scarce fish and lows and
maybe if I'm probably fear 'fl if I
allow fear to be my my basis of choice
then all I'll struggle to be the one who
either a gets it or even better gets to
be the one who makes the determination I
want to be the boss if there's gonna be
a boss I want to be the boss first I
want to be the boss's crony
to get past that you have to find a way
to get past that as the basis of choice
and it's a very this is a very nuanced
thing I'm saying I don't mean be
foolhardy I don't mean numb yourself to
the reality of the possibility of
privation what I mean is to not allow
that to be the basis of your choice to
go deeper than that not to to to ignore
it but actually to recognize that it's a
real thing it's a fundamental thing it's
a part of reality but it's not the fun
most fundamental part of reality below
that deeper than that is that sense of
well in this particular parable we love
which is deeper than fear and if you can
anchor in that then you begin to
recognize that oh oh if we voluntarily
associate in this space of peace we can
in fact get past this problem this
necessity to begin competing with who's
gonna be the boss and who's gonna be the
crony of the boss and most importantly
who's gonna eat me who's not gonna eat
and it has always been thus rites if you
think about it as a as a narrative of
the human experience
it's just contrived to remind us of the
fact that when we move ourselves into a
mindset of scarcity when we mover are
moved from a basis of fear we may
believe that we have solved a problem
but we in fact have bitten off the
biggest problem of all which will net
have inevitably and now now we're in
Gerard land we've anchored ourselves
deeply in Gerard land we know how that
story ends and therefore we must always
be mindful of the necessity of choosing
not to go there the necessity of
choosing even when it is at its most
challenging to be anchored in that sense
of love to create the space of peace to
voluntarily associate and from there is
the only path that leads us into a good
future
you